Myron J. Files Papers MS166
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Myron J. Files Papers
1952 -- 1984
1941 -- 1984
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Files, Myron J.
MS166
0.75 Linear Feet
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into one series.
Biographical / Historical
Myron J. Files (1892-1984) served as a professor in the English Department at Tufts from 1914 to 1955. Myron Files was born in Fairfield, Maine, on May 5th, 1892. After graduating from Dartmouth College in 1914, Myron J. Files began his career at Tufts as an Instructor of English. While teaching, he also pursued his A.M. from Harvard University, which he received in 1916. On August 17th, 1917, Files married Esther Bockius, a cousin of the artist Andrew Wyeth. He then served in World War I until 1918. In 1918, Myron Files resumed his career as an instructor in the English Department at Tufts. He was promoted to Assistant Professor in 1923 and to Associate Professor in 1940. In 1945 he became the William Goldwaithe Professor of Rhetoric. He continued to teach under that title until his retirement in 1955.
After his retirement from Tufts, Myron Files moved to a farm in Appleton, Maine, where he continued his favorite pastimes, gardening and sketching. He also contributed frequent columns to a Massachusetts newspaper, Ipswich Today. Esther and Myron Files' three children; Myron J. Jr., George Everett, and Flora Ann, all attended Tufts. Myron J. Files died in Maine in November 1984 at the age of 92.
Custodial History
This collection was originally housed in the DCA vertical files, but was pulled due to the historical significance and size of the collection. The folders were kept in Russell Miller's order and re-named according to content.
Related Materials
MS007, John A. Holmes, papers 1813-1976, DCA
MS146, Donald J. Winslow, papers 1918-2001, DCA
MS117, Russell E. Miller, papers 1853-1986, DCA
Scope and Contents
The collection is composed of articles, correspondence, employment records, photographs and sketches. Most material dates from Files' retirement in 1955 until his death in 1984. The collection includes correspondence and sketches sent to Tufts Professor of History, Russell Miller, and Tufts presidents Jean Mayer, Nils Wessell, and Burton Hallowell, as well as Boston University professor Donald Winslow. The collection also contains a number of Files' sketches and jottings depicting and commenting on a wide range of subjects from nuclear proliferation to rain on your birthday. A number of his articles from Ipswich Today are also included.
Faculty papers; Holmes, John; Winslow, Donald J.; Miller, Russell E.
- Letters, articles, and sketches, 1941 -- 1984; 1952 -- 1984; MS166.001; 0.75 Linear Feet
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains articles, correspondence, and sketches documenting the period after Myron J. Files' retirement in 1955 up until his death in 1984. Few items date from before 1955. The series includes a considerable amount of correspondence between Files and Professor Donald Winslow and Ms. Charlotte Lindwin, as well as letters between Files and Russell Miller. Please note the sketch of Russell Miller drawn by Myron Files. This series also contains exchanges between Files and Tufts presidents Jean Mayer, Nils Wessel, and Burton C. Hallowell, including some sketches. Administrative records and letters regarding Myron Files' retirement from Tufts, and changes in retirement policies and annuity are also included. Also included are some articles written by Files published in a Massachusetts newspaper, Ipswich Today. A small box of sketches and jottings by Files document his musing and opinions. Also of note is a poem written by John Holmes about Prof. Myron Files on the event of his retirement.
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged alphabetically
  Conditions Governing Access
  Open for research.
  - Correspondence w/ Mr. & Mrs. D. Winslow (1 of 6), 1982; MS166.001.001.00001 (Box 1)
    This folder contains correspondence from 2009 between Archivist Susanne Belovari and Charlotte Winslow regarding the Winslow's friendship and communication with Myron Files.
  - Correspondence w/ Mr. & Mrs. D. Winslow (2 of 6), 1981; MS166.001.001.00002 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence w/ Mr. & Mrs. D. Winslow (3 of 6), 1981 -- 1982; MS166.001.001.00003 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence w/ Mr. & Mrs. D. Winslow (4 of 6), 1981; MS166.001.001.00004 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence w/ Mr. & Mrs. D. Winslow (5 of 6), 1984; MS166.001.001.00005 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence w/ Mr. & Mrs. D. Winslow (6 of 6), 1981 -- 1982; MS166.001.001.00006 (Box 1)
  - Files, Myron J. [Articles and correspondence 1 of 2], 1954 -- 1983; MS166.001.001.00007 (Box 1)
    This folder contains letters from Myron Files to Russel Miller as well as an article written about Files by John Holmes.
  - Files, Myron J. [Articles and correspondence 2 of 2], 1983; MS166.001.001.00008 (Box 1)
    This folder contains a sketch by Myron Files of Russell Miller accompanied by a letter.
  - Files, Myron J. [Retirement 1 of 5], 1941 -- 1982; MS166.001.001.00009 (Box 1)
    This folder contains personal financial information about Myron Files' retirement annuity.
  - Files, Myron J. [Retirement 2 of 5], 1975; MS166.001.001.00010 (Box 1)
    This folder contains sketches and correspondence sent between President Burton C. Hallowell and Myron Files.
  - Files, Myron J. [Retirement 3 of 5], 1980; MS166.001.001.00011 (Box 1)
    This folder contains sketches and correspondence sent between President Jean Mayer and Myron Files.
  - Files, Myron J. [Retirement 4 of 5], 1981; MS166.001.001.00012 (Box 1)
  - Files, Myron J. [Retirement 5 of 5], 1981; MS166.001.001.00013 (Box 1)
    This folder contains sketches to President Jean Mayer by Myron Files.
  - [Original Sketches], 1970 -- 1984; MS166.001.002.00001 (Box 2)
    These sketches were originally found in an envelope labeled: "Files, Myron J. Original Etchings and Newspaper Articles." This box contains a sketch of Russell Miller.